<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************

*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<chapter xml:id="derivatives" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Derivatives</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>
            There are two problems that inspired the creation of calculus.
            The first is the tangent line problem, or rate of change problem.
            This problem is concerned with determining how a quantity <m>f(x)</m> changes as <m>x</m> varies.
            We will focus on this problem and its solution, derivatives, for the next two chapters.
            Afterwards, we will focus on the area problem, the second problem that inspired the creation of calculus.
        </p>
    </introduction>
    <section xml:id="section-the-definition-of-the-derivative">
        <title>The Definition of the Derivative</title>
        <subsection xml:id="subsection-tangent-lines">
            <title>Tangent Lines</title>
            <p>
                Consider <m>f(x) = x^{2}</m>.
                If we graph this, we get a parabola.
                What we'd like to do is to find a way to describe how quickly this parabola is changing at a point, i.e. find the "slope" of the parabola.
                One way to try to deal with this is to use <term>secant lines</term>.
                Recall that the secant line through the points <m>(a,f(a))</m> and <m>(b,f(b))</m> has slope <m>\frac{f(b) - f(a)}{b-a}</m>, which is just the average rate of change of <m>f</m> from <m>x=a</m> to <m>x=b</m>.
                If <m>b</m> is very close to <m>a</m>, then the slope of the secant line through these points should be a good approximation to the "slope" of <m>f(x) = x^{2}</m> at the point <m>x=a</m>.
            </p>
            <example xml:id="example-secant-lines-on-a-parabola">
                <title>Secant lines on a parabola</title>
                <statement>
                    <p>
                        Let <m>f(x) = x^{2}</m>.
                        Find the slope of the secant line through <m>(2,f(2))</m> and <m>(x,f(x))</m>.
                    </p>
                </statement>
                <solution>
                    <p>
                        Since the slope of the secant line is the average rate of change, we get that the slope must be equal to
                        <me>\frac{f(x) - f(2)}{x-2} = \frac{x^{2} - 4}{x-2} = x+2.</me>
                    </p>
                </solution>
            </example>
            <p>
                What <xref ref="example-secant-lines-on-a-parabola" text="type-global" /> is telling us is that if <m>x\approx2</m>, then the slope of <m>f(x) = x^{2}</m> at <m>x=2</m> should be very close to <m>x+2</m>, the slope of the secant line.
                Now we'll do a trick that shows up everywhere in calculus, and is the entire reason we introduced limits in the first place. 
                We'll make this approximation exact by taking a limit.
                In particular, we'll say that the slope of <m>f(x) = x^{2}</m> should be equal to
                <me>\lim_{x\to2}\frac{f(x)-f(2)}{x-2} = \lim_{x\to2}(x+2) = 4.</me>
                This is the slope of the <term>tangent line</term> to <m>f(x) = x^{2}</m> at <m>x=2</m>.
                Instead of an average rate of change over an interval <m>[2,x]</m>, we now have an <term>instantaneous rate of change</term> at a point <m>x=2</m>.
            </p>
            <definition xml:id="definition-tangent-lines">
                <title>Tangent Lines</title>
                <statement>
                    <p>
                        The tangent line to a curve <m>y=f(x)</m> through a point <m>(a,f(a))</m> is the line passing through <m>(a,f(a))</m> with slope given by
                        <me>\lim_{x\to a}\frac{f(x)-f(a)}{x-a},</me>
                        assuming this limit exists.
                        The slope of the tangent line represents the slope of the graph of <m>f(x)</m> at <m>a</m> and gives the instantaneous rate of change of <m>f(x)</m> at <m>x=a</m>.
                    </p>
                </statement>
            </definition>
            <example xml:id="example-tangent-line-to-a-root">
                <title>Tangent line to a root</title>
                <statement>
                    <p>
                        Find the equation of the tangent line to <m>y=\sqrt{x}</m> through the point <m>(4,2)</m>.
                    </p>
                </statement>
                <solution>
                    <p>
                        We need two things to find the equation of a line: the slope of the line and a point on the line.
                        Since we know the tangent line has to pass through <m>(4,2)</m>, we just need to find the slope.
                        The slope is given by
                        <me>\lim_{x\to 4}\frac{\sqrt{x}-2}{x-4} = \lim_{x\to4}\frac{x-4}{(x-4)(\sqrt{x}+2)} = \frac{1}{4}.</me>
                        Hence the equation of the tangent line through <m>(4,2)</m> is
                        <me>y-2 = \frac{1}{4}(x-4).</me>
                    </p>
                </solution>
            </example>
            <p>
                As a reminder, the slope of the tangent line represents the slope, or instantaneous rate of change, of the function.
            </p>
            <example xml:id="example-velocity-from-position">
                <title>Velocity from position</title>
                <statement>
                    <p>
                        The displacement (i.e. position) of a particle moving in a straight line is described by the function <m>s(t) = 3t^{2} - 5t</m>.
                        Find the velocity, or instantaneous rate of change, of the particle at <m>t=3</m>.
                    </p>
                </statement>
                <solution>
                    <p>
                        
                    </p>
                </solution>
            </example>
        </subsection>
    </section>
</chapter>