<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************

*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<chapter xml:id="limits" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Limits of Functions</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>
            At its heart, calculus is just the mathematicals of change.
            In particular, calculus provides the tools necessary to describe how a function changes.
            Since a function can be used to represent many quantities that appear in real life, calculus therefore gives us a way to study how many different quantities (such as temperature, acceleration, energy of a signal, etc.) can change.
            But before we can start using calculus, we need to come up with the proper language to describe it.
            The language we will need to develop is that of the <em>limit of a function</em>.
        </p>
    </introduction>
    
    <section xml:id="section-the-limit-of-a-function">
        <title>The Limit of a Function</title> 
        <subsection xml:id="subsection-motivating-limits">
            <title>Motivating Limits</title>
            <p>
                Imagine creating a mathematical valley out of the graph of <m>f(x) = x^{2}</m>, and in this valley walks a mathematical ant.
                The ant is walking towards the place on the hill directly above <m>x = -\frac{1}{2}</m>.
                At <m>x=-2</m>, the ant is <m>4</m> units above the ground.
                At <m>x=-1</m>, the ant is now <m>1</m> unit above the ground.
                As the ant moves towards <m>x=-\frac{1}{2}</m>, its height above the ground gets closer and closer to <m>\frac{1}{4}</m>.
                To say it more clearly, and because modern calculus is built on this idea, <em>as the ant approaches</em> the point above <m>x = -\frac{1}{2}</m>, its <em>height above the ground approaches</em> the value <m>\frac{1}{4}</m>.
                In other words, the <em>limit</em> of <m>f(x) = x^{2}</m> as <m>x</m> approaches <m>-\frac{1}{2}</m> is <m>\frac{1}{4}</m>.
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure-math-valley">
                <image width="50%">
                    <asymptote>
                        import graph;
                        size(200,IgnoreAspect);

                        real f(real x) {return x^2;}

                        draw(graph(f,-2,2), deepblue);
                        
                        dot((-2,f(-2)), red);
                        draw((-2,0)--(-2,f(-2)), red+dashed);
                        dot((-1,f(-1)), red);
                        draw((-1,0)--(-1,f(-1)), red+dashed);
                        dot((-.5,f(-.5)), red);
                        draw((-.5,0)--(-.5,f(-.5)), red+dashed);

                        yaxis("$y$",ymin=-.1,ymax=f(2.1),RightTicks(Label(Fill(white))),EndArrow);
                        xaxis("$x$",xmin=-5,xmax=5,LeftTicks,EndArrow);
                    </asymptote>
                </image>
                <caption>A mathematical valley minus a mathematical ant.</caption>
            </figure>
            <p>
                Remember that a function <m>f</m> of the variable <m>x</m> is just a rule that turns one number, <m>x</m>, into another number, <m>f(x)</m>.
                So the idea that the <em>limit of a function</em> is trying to express is what happens to the number <m>f(x)</m> (the output) as the number <m>x</m> (the input) approaches some particular value.
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    Actually, functions are much more general than this.
                    But for calculus, it won't hurt us to view functions in this way.
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                We're not quite ready to define the limit of a function precisely, but we can point one thing out right away: <em>the limit of a function requires two pieces of information: the function itself and the number that <m>x</m> is approaching.</em>
                The limit should then be whatever number that <m>f(x)</m> is approaching.
            </p>
        </subsection>
    </section>
</chapter>