<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************

*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<chapter xml:id="techniques-of-integration" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Techniques of Integration</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>
            This chapter focuses on several techniques for evaluating complicated integrals.
            As the tools in this chapter are in general more complicated than those that appeared in <xref ref="integrals" text="type-global" />, you should only use these if algebraic simplification or substitution are insufficient to compute an integral.
        </p>
    </introduction>
    <section xml:id="section-integration-by-parts">
        <title>Integration by Parts</title>
        <p>
            Suppose we want to integrate <m>f(x) = x\sin x</m>.
            This can't be simplified using algebra (since integrals don't split up over products!) and substitution probably won't be very helpful, since <m>f(x)</m> does not already contain an "inside function" that we could replace.
            The integration tools that we have are unable to compute this integral, so we need to develop more tools!
        </p>
        <p>
            Recall that the substitution method for solving integrals from <xref ref="section-substitution" text="type-global" /> is derived from the chain rule.
            In fact, by <xref ref="theorem-fundamental-theorem-of-calculus" text="type-global" /> every derivative rule available to us also provides a corresponding integration rule.
            So perhaps the integration rule corresponding to the product rule can help us to integrate products. 
            We call this method <em>integration by parts</em>.
        </p>
        <theorem xml:id="theorem-integration-by-parts">
            <title>Integration by Parts</title>
            <idx><h>integration techniques</h><h>integration by parts</h></idx>
            <statement>
                <p>
                    Let <m>f(x)</m> and <m>g(x)</m> be continuous functions, with <m>g(x)</m> differentiable.
                    Then
                </p>
                <me>\int f(x)g'(x)\,dx = f(x)g(x) - \int g(x)f'(x)\,dx.</me>
            </statement>
            <proof>
                <p>
                    By the product rule, we have <m>\dv{}{x}[f(x)g(x)] = f(x)g'(x) + f'(x)g(x)</m>.
                    Rearranging this, we have
                    <me>f(x)g'(x) = [f(x)g(x)]' - f'(x)g(x).</me>
                    Finally, we can integrate both sides to get
                    <me>\int f(x)g'(x)\,dx = f(x)g(x) - \int g(x)f'(x)\,dx.</me>
                </p>
            </proof>
        </theorem>
        <p>
            A useful way to remember the integration by parts method is as follows:
            <men xml:id="equation-integration-by-parts">\int u\,dv = uv - \int v\,du.</men>
            Integration by parts can be used to integrate products of functions <em>that can't already be evaluated by simpler means</em>.
        </p>
        <example xml:id="example-using-the-integration-by-parts-formula">
            <title>Using the Integration by Parts Formula</title>
            <statement>
                <p>
                    Compute <m>\int x\sin x\,dx</m>.
                </p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <p>
                    To use <xref ref="equation-integration-by-parts" text="type-global" />, we need to write <m>\int x\sin x\,dx</m> in the form <m>\int u\,dv</m>.
                    Once we have <m>u</m> and <m>dv</m>, then we can set up the rest of the formula.
                    One thing that can make this method tricky is the fact that we can have many different choices for <m>u</m> and <m>dv</m>; the only thing we need for certain is for <m>u\,dv = x\sin x</m> here.
                    However, if we look at the formula <xref ref="equation-integration-by-parts" text="type-global" /> then we'll see two new terms on the right hand side: <m>du</m> and <m>v</m>, together in the second integral.
                    This means that we'll need to differentiate <m>u</m> and integrate <m>v</m>, and this will suggest what both should be.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Since we need to compute <m>du</m>, then we want <m>u</m> to be easy to differentiate.
                    Similarly, we want <m>dv</m> to be easy to integrate.
                    And since we'd like to be able to compute this integral, we'd also like <m>v\,du</m> to be simpler than <m>u\,dv</m>.
                    Now return to <m>x\sin x</m>.
                    Since <m>x</m> gets simpler if we differentiate it by <m>\sin x</m> doesn't, this suggests that we should set <m>u = x</m>.
                    And since <m>u = x</m>, we must have <m>dv = \sin x\,dx</m> (since <m>dv</m> automatically becomes whatever is left over).
                    With these choices, we have
                </p>
                <md>
                    <mrow>du &amp; = \,dx </mrow>
                    <mrow>v &amp; = -\cos x </mrow>
                </md>
                <p>
                    Therefore
                </p>
                <md>
                    <mrow>\int x\sin x\,dx &amp; = \int u\,dv </mrow>
                    <mrow> &amp; = uv - \int v\,du </mrow>
                    <mrow> &amp; = -x\cos x - \int (-\cos x)\,dx </mrow>
                    <mrow> &amp; = -x\cos x + \int\cos x\,dx </mrow>
                    <mrow> &amp; = -x\cos x + \sin x + C. </mrow>
                </md>
            </solution>
        </example>
        <aside>
            <p>
                You may be wondering why we didn't include an arbitrary constant when we found <m>v</m> in <xref ref="example-using-the-integration-by-parts-formula" text="type-global" />.
                This is because including an arbitrary constant here doesn't affect the final answer.
                It's certainly not incorrect to include one here, but it adds more work than is already necessary.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            When using the integration by parts method, it's usually a good idea to choose <m>u</m> to be the polynomial portion of your integrand if there is one.
            This is because polynomials become simpler when they're differentiated.
            However, there are examples where <m>u</m> should be something else.
        </p>
        <example xml:id="example-integrals-involving-the-natural-logarithm">
            <title>Integrals Involving the Natural Logarithm</title>
            <statement>
                <p>
                    Determine <m>\int 3x^{2}\ln x\,dx</m>.
                </p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <p>
                    Since we need to integrate a product, and we can't easily do so with <m>u</m>-substitution or algebra, we'll try integration by parts.
                    We could pick <m>u = 3x^{2}</m>, and this is certainly easy to differentiate so we can find <m>du</m>.
                    However, doing so leaves us with <m>dv = \ln x</m>, which is tricky to integrate, but is easy to differentiate.
                    So we'll try setting <m>u = \ln x</m> and <m>dv = 3x^{2}\,dx</m>.
                    Then
                </p>
                <md>
                    <mrow>du &amp; = \frac{1}{x}\,dx </mrow>
                    <mrow>v &amp; = x^{3} </mrow>
                </md>
                <p>
                    and so
                </p>
                <md>
                    <mrow>\int 3x^{2}\ln x\,dx &amp; = uv - \int v\,du </mrow>
                    <mrow> &amp; = x^{3}\ln x - \int \frac{x^{3}}{x}\,dx </mrow>
                    <mrow> &amp; = x^{3}\ln x - \frac{1}{3}x^{3} + C. </mrow>
                </md>
            </solution>
        </example>
        <example xml:id="example-an-integral-from-differential-equations">
            <title>An Integral from Differential Equations</title>
            <statement>
                <p>
                    An important concept in the field of differential equations is that of the <em>Laplace transform</em>.
                    In the process of computing the Laplace transform of <m>\cos t</m>, an integral similar to <m>\int e^{t}\cos t\,dt</m> appears.
                    Determine this integral.
                </p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <p>
                    Here, it doesn't make much difference what we select for <m>u</m> or <m>dv</m>, since both <m>e^{t}</m> and <m>\cos t</m> are easy to differentiate and integrate, while neither becomes simpler.
                    But since we're integrating a product, we'll try to use integration by parts anyway and hope for the best.
                    To that end, let <m>u = e^{t}</m> and <m>dv = \cos t</m>.
                    Then <m>du = e^{t}\,dt</m> and <m>v = \sin t</m>, which gives
                </p>
                <md>
                    <mrow>\int e^{t}\cos t\,dt &amp; = uv - \int v\,du </mrow>
                    <mrow> &amp; = e^{t}\sin t - \int e^{t}\sin t\,dt. </mrow>
                </md>
                <p>
                    As expected, the new integral isn't any simpler than the one that we started with.
                    However, it's not any more <em>complicated</em> either.
                    So we'll try integration by parts on the new integral as well, with <m>u = e^{t}, du = e^{t}\,dt, dv = \sin t\,dt</m> and <m>v = -\cos t</m>.
                    Then
                </p>
                <me>\int e^{t}\sin t\,dt = -e^{t}\cos t + \int e^{t}\cos t\,dt.</me>
                <p>
                    So we have
                </p>
                <md>
                    <mrow>\int e^{t}\cos t\,dt &amp; = e^{t}\sin t - (-e^{t}\cos t + \int e^{t}\cos t\,dt) </mrow>
                    <mrow> &amp; = e^{t}\sin t + e^{t}\cos t - \int e^{t}\cos t\,dt </mrow>
                </md>
                <p>
                    There is something very strange about this equation: <em>the same integral appears on both sides</em>.
                    This is no longer a calculus problem, it's an algebra problem!
                    Solving for the integral algebraically (and including the arbitrary constant!) gives
                    <me>\int e^{t}\cos t\,dt = \frac{e^{t}\sin t + e^{t}\cos t}{2} + C.</me>
                </p>
            </solution>
        </example>
        <p>
            Integrals with integrands of the form <m>P(x)e^{x}</m>, <m>P(x)\sin x</m> or <m>P(x)\cos x</m> (where <m>P(x)</m> is a polynomials) can be successfully evaluated using the <em>tabular method</em>.
        </p>
        <example xml:id="example-the-tabular-method">
            <title>The Tabular Method</title>
            <statement>
                <p>
                    Evaluate <m>\int (3x^{2} - 2x)\cos3x\,dx</m>.
                </p>
            </statement>
        </example>
        <p>
            Integration by parts also applies to definite integrals.
            You only need to remember to carry the limits through.
        </p>
        <example xml:id="example-sign-of-a-sine">
            <title>Sign of a Sine</title>
            <statement>
                <p>
                    Let <m>f(x) = x^{2}\sin x</m>.
                    Does <m>f(x)</m> tend to be positive or negative along <m>[0,2\pi]</m>?
                </p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <p>
                    We need to check the sign of <m>\int_{0}^{2\pi}x^{2}\sin x\,dx</m>.
                    Using the tabular method, we get
                    <me>\int_{0}^{2\pi}x^{2}\sin x\,dx = [-x^{2}\cos x + 2x\sin x + 2\cos x]_{0}^{2\pi} = -4\pi^{2} + 4\pi - 2.</me>
                    Since this is negative, <m>f(x)</m> tends to be negative along <m>[0,2\pi]</m>.
                </p>
            </solution>
        </example>
    </section>
</chapter>